Guide to the National Maritime Union Photographs PHOTOS.044
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Maritime Union Photographs
circa 1940s-1950s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Maritime Union of America
Economic Cooperation Administration
Haas, Ernst, 1921-1986
Rutgers University. Libraries. Special Collections and University Archives
Herson, Gene
Prometheus Research Library
PHOTOS.044
0.75 Linear Feet in 1 oversize flat box and 1 folder.
The National Maritime Union (NMU) was an American labor union founded in May 1937 and led by Joseph Curran. The collection contains black and white photographs of NMU activities mostly in the 1940s and 1950s, as well as photographs of merchant seamen and shipping in Marseille, France made by photographer Ernst Haas for the Economic Development Corporation, a United States agency that administered the Marshall Plan. The collection also includes films produced by the NMU.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Rutgers University Special Collections in 1989; additional materials were donated by Gene Herson on behalf of the Prometheus Library in circa 1996. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1982.044, NPA.1989.001, and NPA.1996.017.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 3 series. Items in Series II are arranged according to an original numbering scheme on the back of the photographs.
Series I: National Maritime Union Photographs
Series II: ECA Photographs by Ernst Haas
Series III: Films
Historical/Biographical Note
The National Maritime Union of America (NMU), which represented merchant marine workers, was formed in 1937, as a split from the International Seafarer's Union, which was affiliated with the American Federation of Labor (AFL). At its first convention in 1937, the NMU joined the Committee for Industrial Organizations (CIO). A crucial role in its formation was played by former members of the Communist-led Marine Workers Industrial Union. Among the notable reforms achieved by the union's Communist-dominated leadership was "checkerboarding," the side-by-side racial integration of sailors' sleeping quarters. By the end of World War II, the NMU had nearly 100,000 members. The union was founded and led by Joseph Curran, who served as NMU president until 1981.
During World War II, the alliance of Communists and non-communists in the union was weakened by charges that the Communists, in their desire to maximize productivity in order to aid the Soviet Union, did not aggressively defend sailors' interests. The Cold War exacerbated the ideological divide, and in 1948, the NMU's Communist leadership and its allies were defeated in union elections and expelled.
In 1950, the NMU's Welfare plan was established, providing seamen with health, accident and life insurance benefits. In 1954 a pension component was added. Curran's successor, Shannon Wall, was not well-received by a strong minority of the union, led by James Morrissey. In 2001, the NMU merged with the Seafarers International Union of North America, which originally represented West Coast merchant mariners.
Related Archival Materials
The National Maritime Union Records are held by the Special Collections and University Archives of Rutgers University.
For more materials on the National Maritime Union at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Archives, see the National Maritime Union Printed Ephemera Collection (PE008), Marine Workers Historical Collection (TAM.125), Maritime Workers / National Maritime Union Research Files of Bruce Nelson (TAM.585), Marine Workers Historical Collection Oral Histories (OH.030), and the Jake Green National Maritime Union Photographs (PHOTOS.047).
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of two groups of photographs and seven films. One group of photographs consists of approximately one hundred black and white prints of various sizes, as well as contact sheets, and negatives document the activities of the National Maritime Union (NMU) mostly in the 1940s and 1950s. The other group of 32 black and white prints were made by photographer Ernst Haas, possibly between 1948 and 1952, for the Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA), the administrative arm of the Marshall Plan. These photographs document the lives of merchant seamen, shipping, and post-war economic development in Marseille, France. The films were produced by the NMU.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Merchant mariners -- Labor unions -- United States.; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; National Maritime Union of America; Seafarers International Union of North America; Smith, Ferdinand; Rutgers University. Libraries. Special Collections and University Archives; Herson, Gene; Prometheus Research Library
- Series I: National Maritime Union Photographs, circa 1940s-circa 1950s
  Scope and Content Note
  This series consists of approximately one hundred black and white prints of various sizes, as well as contact sheets, and negatives documenting activities of the National Maritime Union (NMU) mostly in the 1940s and 1950s. Groups of photographs include portraits of NMU members and leaders; the opening of the Upgrading and Sea Safety School in New York City in 1943; a 1944 "Maritime Day" celebration with black, white and Hispanic members and their families; a "Safety at Sea" exhibit with NMU leaders; room shots of the Sixth NMU Convention; group portraits of NMU committees from 1947; several images of ships and mess halls; and a circa 1950s hiring hall shape-up. Individuals pictured include NMU president Joseph Curran, treasurer Ferdinand Smith, Mayor Fiorello Laguardia and photographer Berenice Abbott. Several prints, with corresponding contact sheets and negatives, appear to have been taken over the course of a single day inside the NMU's hiring hall in New York City, possibly in the 1970s.
  - General, circa 1940s-circa 1970s; cuid15007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portraits of NMU and Labor Leaders, circa 1940s; cuid15008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Maritime Day (1 of 2), 1944; cuid15009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maritime Day (2 of 2), 1944; cuid15010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Safety At Sea" Exhibit, circa 1940s; cuid15011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Miscellaneous NMU Photos (Includes ships, mess hall, demonstration against Westbrook Pegler, Christmas Party)], circa 1940s; cuid15012 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General [(Includes Hiring hall "shape-up"; NMU 6th Convention)], circa 1940s-circa 1950s; cuid15013 (Box Shared Tamiment OS001)
- Series II: Economic Cooperation Administration Photos by Ernst Haas, circa 1948-1952; cuid15014 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Historical/Biographical Note
  Ernst Haas (1921-1986) was born in Vienna and took up photography after World War II. His first widely published pictures depicted returning prisoners of war in Austria and brought him to the attention of Life magazine, which published his photo essay "Homecoming." At the invitation of Robert Capa, Haas joined the cooperative Magnum Photos in 1949, developing close associations with Capa, Henri Cartier-Bresson, and Werner Bishof. In 1951 Haas moved to New York and continued to take black and white assignments for magazines while experimenting with color film. His color photo essay of New York City was published in Life in 1953 and was a turning point in the acceptance of color photography as an art form and abstraction as a photographic style. Haas became president of Magnum in 1959. Throughout his career, he worked in photojournalism, advertising, and as a still photographer for films, bridging the gap between photojournalism and the use of photography as a medium for artistic expression. He wrote four books during his lifetime, including "The Creation" (1971).
  The series contains 32 black and white prints made by photographer Ernst Haas, possibly between 1948 and 1952, for the Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA), the administrative arm of the Marshall Plan. The photographs appear to document economic development, shipping, and the lives of black and white merchant seamen in Marseille, France. They include portraits of workers at work, in cafes and at home with their families, images of ports, ships, a railroad yard, building construction, post-war housing developments, and signs, political posters and graffiti in French.
- Series III: Films, undated
  - Americans at Work, undated; cuid15015 (Box Shared Tamiment 133, Reel cuid15015)
    Scope and Contents
    A 16mm projection print. Handwritten annotations on the housing include the following terms: "AFL-CIO", "N211-38 Maritime."
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Format: 16mm
  - Target Labor, undated; cuid15016 (Box Shared Tamiment 131, Reel cuid15016)
    A 16mm print produced and distributed by the National Maritime Union's Pilot, Education and Publicity Department. "Black Thursday" is written by hand on the original film can.
  - Merchant Marine, undated; cuid15017 (Box Shared Tamiment 131, Reel cuid15017)
    A 16mm print produced and distributed by the National Maritime Union's Pilot, Education, and Publicity Department. "WWII Convoys" is written by hand on the original film can.
    Format: 16mm, Length: 630'
  - Fight for Maritime Union, undated; cuid15018; 2 film reels Duplicates 16mm (Reel cuid15018A, Reel cuid15018B)
    Format: 16mm, Duration: 27 min., Sound
    Two duplicate 16mm film prints produced and distributed by the National Maritime Union's Pilot, Education, and Publicity Department. Handwritten annotations on the original film can include: "with talk by Curran" and "Print No. 1."
  - [Salvador], undated; cuid15019 (Reel cuid15019)
  - Guilty Men, undated; cuid15022 (Box Shared Tamiment 166, 16mm film reels cuid15022)
  - Deadline for Action, undated; cuid15023 (Reel cuid15023)